Now in the last lesson we learned about the gesture detector and we added it as a parent to our reusable
card.
At the top the ones with are male and female icons.
And we created a method called update color that allows us to select one of these genders and we have
to activate these cards by changing their color.
Now at the moment our code works just fine.
But it's a little bit wordy and also there's a few things that aren't not so great.
And the first thing that comes to mind is the fact that we're passing in a integer to represent a gender.
So we're saying that one is going to equal male and two is going to equal female.
So that's why we're checking to see if the gender is one then that means the male card got pressed.
But if the gender was two then that means the female card got pressed.
Now as you can imagine if you came back to this code in six months time or if somebody else was looking
at it they might get a little bit confused because it doesn't make a lot of sense.
And even though we have a lot of comments here it's not great.
So how can we solve this in this lesson.
We're going to address all of this by learning a concept in programming that is super useful WHICH ARE
ENEMIES IN ARMS STAND FOR enumeration.
And if you look it up in a dictionary it means the action of establishing the number of something.
And that's kind of what we've been doing here right.
We've been establishing that the male gender is the number one and the female gender is the number two.
But this is super painful and quite confusing.
But in programming this need crops up very frequently.
Say if you're trying to encode different types of cars in your app and you say that we have this thing
called car type and if it's equal to one then it's convertible if it's equal to two then it's an SUV.
If it's three then it's a hatchback.
Now these numbers don't actually inherently have any meaning.
And we're actually assigning it a meaning and trying to remember it down the line and trying to force
other people who we work with also to follow this convention and that's difficult.
But imagine if instead we can actually give it a word which already has meaning.
So if we said that the first one has a car type of DOT convertible and the second one was Dot SUV or
third one was Dot hatchback.
That makes a lot more sense and is a lot easier to work with and you can see at a glance in the code
what it is that we're talking about.
We're coding up these different types of cars.
If you imagine that we already have billions which we know to be either on or off or true or false and
is a bit like a light bulb it's very binary right.
It has two states on and off.
But what if we wanted more states then a light bulb can hold.
Well then that's where we kind of start using e names and I would say that you names are almost a bit
like a blender where you have multiple options right.
You might have a high setting you might have a low setting you might have a medium or a juice or a blend
or alter blend whatever it may be and it's more than just on or off.
There's many different options and that's exactly what we use in terms for when there's a lot of different
options that we want to be able to encode and not just have to rely on numbers.
And we can actually give each of the options a name that has meaning in inner looks like this in dot
we first start out with the keyword in them to show that we're creating an enum and then we give the
enum a name.
So it could be car type or it could be gender but the naming convention for enum names are the same
as class names.
So there are camel cased but they start off with a capital letter and then we have a set of curly braces
that describes each of the different types.
So say Type A Type B type C or hatchback who pay convertible.
And then when we actually need to use the E enum then we can simply write in name dot type A or dot
type B let's head over to a dart pad to see this in a little bit more detail.
Now let's say that we had a class of car and previously we only had things such as number of C or number
of doors which makes a lot of sense to use an integer four right five doors is literally an integer.
But if we wanted to encode a card style then we might have to use an integer and we have to make a note
to ourselves that remember that you know if this is one then that means it's a hatchback.
And if it's a two then it means it's an SUV et cetera which is quite painful but it does mean that if
we decided to initialize our car.
Say we create our constructor and we set r this start cost style when we create the car.
Then we could go into our main function and we could create a new car.
So let's it's a data type of car.
Let's call it my car.
And it's going to be equal to a car that's constructed.
And we have to give it a car style and let's say it's equal to an SUV.
My car's an SUV.
Now if you read this line of code it makes absolutely no sense whatsoever to a human unless we add a
whole bunch of comments to say that oh actually this car style too means that I'm creating a new SUV.
Now it's good practice to have comments that explain the logic of your thinking of what your program
does.
But it's not great when you need comments to be able to understand what's actually going on in a particular
line.
And this is a classic case where E numbers can come in and save the day because if we lost all of those
comments and we came along to this code two months later then this makes no sense whatsoever so what
if we created an Ina.
So let's do this here outside of any other classes and we're going to use the E name keyword to say
that we're creating a new enum and the E name is going to have a name which is going to be a capitalized
camel case.
And we're going to call it car type.
And then we open up a set of curly braces and we add all the different car types that we might want
in our program.
So it might have hatchback we might have a SUV and maybe a convertible and let's just add a toupee.
Just for fun.
So we've now got four types of cars and they're enclosed inside an enum and now we can use these car
types.
So instead of having a car style that's represented by an integer we can change the data type to a enum
type.
So our car type and now when we initialize our car style instead of writing one for Q Pay or two for
hatchback we can actually provide the enum as a named value.
So we could write car type dot and you can see that we're really getting all of our values in our dropdown
list.
So let's say that we're creating a new convertible.
Then we've got my car which is created from the car constructor and the property for its car style is
a convertible car type.
Now look at how much better that reads.
Even if I came back to this code a million years later well maybe I'd already be enslaved to the computers.
But either way if I came back to this after a long time this line of code still makes a lot of sense.
So let's head back to our code and here's the challenge for you create agenda in I'm at the top of file
you can't create enemies inside classes so make sure it's outside of any of the other classes maybe
somewhere below the constants and then use that gender enum inside our update color and inside our gesture
detector to be a to say that in this case it was the male car that was pressed.
And in this case it was the female car that was pressed so that we can process it differently inside
this update color method.
So pause the video and try to upgrade your code by using dot in MS
All right.
So first things first we're going to create R E M using the E M keyword and we're just gonna call it
gender but we're going to make sure it's capitalized at the beginning to show that it's not the same
as a variable or a constant.
Now gender is going to have only two different values and it's going to be male and it's going to be
female.
So now we can use this E M gender dot male agenda dot female in our code for example our update color
can now instead of taking a int type input we can have it as a gender type input so we can either leave
that name as gender or if you find that a bit confusing you can change it to selected gender just to
know that it's the name that we're giving the input and now we can check to see that if the selected
gender is equal to not one but gender dot male then we should do all of this but if the select agenda
was instead equal to gender dot female then we would do all of this.
And now in our code here we update color instead of passing in one we can pass in gender dot male and
over here we can pass in gender dot female.
So now look at how much better our code reads when this card has a tab detected we update the state
by updating and update the color and we tell it that the female card was pressed and then it goes into
our update color method and it checks to see if the gender was male that was selected or if the select
agenda was female that was selected and then we carry out all of the rest of this code.
So e names are really useful when you have more than one option for a property.
So things such as car types or high low medium settings or in our case genders male female etc. It's
really really useful to clean up our code and make it more expressive but still our problem is that
our code is so wordy that it's actually painful to look at.
So in the next lesson we're going to learn another thing that we get access to in dot which are ternary
operators and we're going to clean up all of this to reduce it down to maybe one or two lines of code.
So if you're ready for all of that magic head over to the next lesson.